BORIS OSIPCHUK

SUMMARY

I am a technology leader with 24 years of providing software development expertise in manufacturing, financial and oil & gas industries, helping companies release architecturally sound products and services faster, as well as with greater quality. I can quickly build release teams and make them productive, identify and fix problem areas within them, improving communication and performance, so the deliverables are always on time and on budget.

SKILLS

Strategic thinking, operational excellence, process improvement, team leadership, effective communication and collaboration, business acumen, innovation and creativity, project management, vendor relationships, software development methodologies and architecture, traditional and cloud infrastructure, cloud computing, microservices, mobile and web development, cybersecurity, data science, data governance/curation/warehousing, UI/UX, DevSecOps, emerging technologies.

EXPERIENCE

HEAD OF SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT AND ARCHITECTURE
BAOSOFT CONSULTING
HOUSTON, TX
APR 2023 – CURRENT

- Delivering DecisionSpace connector to Paradise AI platform.
- Delivered a plan to strategically modernize client's hardware infrastructure and software architecture to improve their value proposition to customers.
- Documented current infrastructure and architecture using C4 framework.
- Analyzed the status of OSDU platform and its viability for next gen architecture.
- Analyzed Storage and Compute offerings from major cloud providers and made recommendations to ensure future trends will be considered.
- Establishing evolutionary architecture practice by adopting Architecture as a Code paradigm and starting Architectural Decision Record (ADR) database.

Infrastructure Stack: Dell, nVidia, AWS, Azure

Software Stack: Windows, Unix (CentOS), C4, Structurizr, OSDU, Microsoft SQL Server, .NET, CUDA, OpenInventor (3D Viewer), GeoToolkit.NET (2D Viewer), C#,

Python, IronPython, Fortran, PSL (proprietary), Batch Scripting (Windows), Microsoft Visual Studio, TFVC, TFS Build, InstallShield, Ranorex, Flexera, TFS, Microsoft Project, SharePoint, Sunsama, Agile, Scrum, Microsoft Teams, GTM, Zoom

HEAD OF SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT AND ARCHITECTURE **HALLIBURTON - BAROID** HOUSTON, TX JAN 2021 - APR 2023

Strategic thinking:

- Devised a plan to strategically grow the organization which has resulted in the addition of 10 full-time positions over 18 months.
- Realized strategic value of Halliburton 4.0 initiative and delivered projects to transition Multi-Chem's APX and Baroid's BaraLogix applications onto iEnergy cloud which resulted in the applications having access to a plethora of APIs from other Halliburton's product service lines, improved deployment times (days to minutes) and reduced Ops running costs (by ~50%). In turn, other Halliburton functions will also have access to Multi-Chem and Baroid APIs which greatly enhances the company's overall value proposition to O&G customers.

Operations:

- Managed an \$8MM budget to lead 3 distributed teams of 100 people (dev managers, product owners, architects, devs, testers, DevDecOps engineers, data, and domain scientists).
- Continuously delivered strategic products (DFG, CFG, BaraLogix, WellSight 20/20, APX, TPBBW, LabSight) to enhance Baroid and Multi-Chem value proposition to various O&G customers, locally and in the cloud (Azure).
- Developed dashboard for presenting monthly status updates of all products which has improved senior management's visibility into software development.

Technical Expertise:

- Recommended and oversaw re-architecture of APX application which has improved client-side performance 2X and end-points performance by 3X, reduced app size, simplified codebase, modularized core components, fixed static analysis errors, improved usability, migrated from MongoDB to MS SQL server (querying performance improved by various degrees), introduced async data loading and improved error handling.
- Oversaw the establishment of data warehouse to enable reporting for Multi-Chem management using Microsoft SQL Server and PowerBI, utilizing nightly ETL process from operational database.

Improving processes:

- Streamlined processes to ensure timely submission of purchase requisitions, execution of SOWs, issue of purchase orders and processing of invoices which ensured more efficient communications with vendors, as well as cutting processing times in half.
- Improved CAPEX/OPEX long-term forecasts which enhanced planning and allocation of resources by 10-20% (also led to reducing vendor invoices errors by 10-20%).
- Established good agile practices for SDLC and ensured all team members receive relevant training that has resulted in increased velocity of up to 20% for product teams.

Business acumen:

 Analyzed cloud costs across Baroid product service line, found gaps in governance and cloud monitoring, recommended improvements to fix the gaps which resulted in 10K/month cost savings and enabled better future oversight.

Leadership:

 Provided mentorship and feedback to direct reports through "check-in" process that enhanced their abilities and ensured good succession planning.

Infrastructure Stack: Azure, HP, Edge Devices.

Software Stack: Windows, Microsoft SQL Server, MongoDB, MySQL, data warehousing, ETL, PowerBI, mobile and web development, .NET Core, C#, Angular, Java Script, RabbitMQ, Microservices, REST API, Okta, SignalR, Swagger, Postman, Microsoft Visual Studio, TFS, TFVC, TFS Build, ADO, Git, InstallShield, Ranorex, Microsoft Project, SharePoint, Sunsama, Agile, ADF(EDF), Microsoft Teams, Appian, JourneyApps.

SR. SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT MANAGER GEOPHYSICAL INSIGHTS HOUSTON, TX DEC 2017 - OCT 2020

Helped to develop the new Al workbench, Paradise®, into a premier product.

Owned software development, project management, DevSecOps, QA, IT:

- Continuously streamlined software development process and resolved any dayto-day impediments.
- Interfaced with external IT company and make decisions on their recommendations.
- Managed licenses for all 3rd party libs used in Paradise development.
- Worked with various vendors to augment software delivery of Paradise.

Reviewed/approved invoices, tracked costs.

Operations:

- Managed a \$3MM budget to lead a team of 15 people (devs, testers, DevDecOps engineer, and domain scientists).
- Delivered Paradise 3.2 (new look and feel, Geobodies, cultures, sculpting, LAS/ASCII imports, Esri map and shape files).
- Delivered Paradise 3.3 (Polygons, Fault Identification and Facies Classification both based on CNN, plugin for Petrel, lift-and-shift" to AWS and Azure).
- Delivered Paradise 3.4 (Well Log Viewer, AASPI on GPU, Paradise appliance).
- Reduced IT security risk by overseeing IT security audit according to CIS controls
 7.1 and ensured that action items were implemented.

Technical expertise:

- Principal contributor to a white paper on next generation architecture for Paradise 4.0.
- Evaluated and made recommendations on several scenarios on how to proceed into the future (gradually moving into cloud-native direction based on CNCF foundation trail map).

Improving processes:

- Conducted complete audit of day-to-day operations and recommended action items which brought confidence and stability to the team (tracking of work on TFS, architecture and design reviews, software development guidelines, test automation).
- Developed release tracking reports for senior management that enabled transparent view into Paradise software development.
- Helped Product Management to develop interface for new functionality that was a point of great contention for the customer.

Leadership:

- Mentored fellow team members in order to enable them to be self-sufficient.
- Gave constant feedback to employees and contractors.
- Advocated to senior management sending team members to various conferences and training, so they can stay up-to-date on latest technological advances (OSDU events, HPC workshops, SEG/EAGE/AAPG conferences, vendor trainings).

Infrastructure Stack: Dell, nVidia, AWS, Azure

Software Stack: Windows, Unix (CentOS), Microsoft SQL Server, .NET, CUDA, OpenInventor (3D Viewer), GeoToolkit.NET (2D Viewer), C#, Python, IronPython, Fortran, PSL (proprietary), Batch Scripting (Windows), Microsoft Visual Studio, TFVC,

TFS Build, InstallShield, Ranorex, Flexera, TFS, Microsoft Project, SharePoint, Sunsama, Agile, Scrum, Microsoft Teams, GTM, Zoom

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT MANAGER
HALLIBURTON - LANDMARK
HOUSTON, TX
MAY 2013 - DEC 2017

Operations:

- Managed a \$5MM budget to lead 5 distributed teams of 50 people (dev managers, architects, devs, testers, DevDecOps engineers, and domain scientists).
- Delivered 4 cadence releases of DS Geosciences 10ep, coordinating the work of about 300 employees across various functions and 2 releases of SeisWorks Suite, StratWorks, ZAP!/FZAP, PostStack Suite, Z-MAP Plus, PetroWorks, TDQ, SpecDecomp, SynTool, Rave, GeoProbe).
- Setup and recruited 5 offshore teams in 2 countries.
- After learning the in-house reporting and time-tracking tool (PST), I have become a go-to person for any upper management questions about organization.
- To maintain a steady pool of incoming talent, I have worked with University Affairs department which involves participating in recruitment fairs and conducting info session presentations with students at various universities, as well as interviewing and recommending interns for hiring.
- Reported to Finance & Accounting department, projecting SW CAP and ensuring accurate time entry for projects across DSG program.
- Collaborated with Legal department assisting employees with H1-B and Green Card processes.
- Worked with 8 different vendors that provide services to R&D.
- Worked with IT to set up a collaboration zone to enable proper networking access for offshore locations that complied with Halliburton policies. Procured licenses to enable development in offshore teams.
- Represented R&D Dev in special Deployment Response team where extremely urgent customer requests were prioritized and addressed.
- Administered TFS and SharePoint for the DSG program.

Improving processes:

In conjunction with other senior managers, I have invented the new Solutions
philosophy for software development that broke the silos within R&D
organization and enabled a more fluid approach to the Software Development
process and better communication.

 I have implemented offshore team development guidelines and ensured that the teams adhered to them. Following best agile practices, I have served as a Scrum Master, utilizing Rally and later TFS for tracking teams' progress.

Leadership:

- Conducted performance appraisals to team members, recommend outstanding employees for promotions and give feedback for improvement to those who struggle.
- Mentored junior employees.
- Resolved conflict situations with employees.
- Worked on R&D reorganization to improve software delivery.
- Organized various training courses for R&D employees that addressed domain and programming skills gaps.

Infrastructure Stack: AWS, Azure, HP

Software Stack: Java, Eclipse RCP, OSGI, SQL, Eclipse IDE, JavaSwing, OpenWorks (Oracle-based proprietary DB), Subversion, QuickBuild, SAP, HP Customer Center, Test Architect, TFS, Microsoft Project, SharePoint, Agile, Scrum, Skype

JAVA DEVELOPER

JAN 2000 - MAY 2013

Cincom Systems, Fifth Third Bank, BTS-IT Inc, O'Neil & Associates, Jackson National Life Insurance, Taylor Communications. (More details are on LinkedIn)

EDUCATION

UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN AT FLINT, B.S IN COMPUTER SCIENCE
UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS AT URBANA-CHAMPAIGN, SELECTED COURSES
IN DATA SCIENCE

CERTIFICATIONS

SUN CERTIFIED PROGRAMMER FOR THE JAVA 2 PLATFORM 1.4

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/boris-osipchuk/

Personal Website: http://www.borisosipchuk.com

TECHNOLOGIES

INFRASTRUCTURE

Azure, AWS, Dell, HP, nVidia

OPERATING SYSTEMS

Windows, UNIX, MacOS, iOS, Android

SOFTWARE LANGUAGES

Java, SQL, HTML/CSS, XML, C++, COBOL, Assembler, Python, C#

APPLICATION SERVERS

Apache HTTP, Apache Tomcat, JBoss, WebSphere

DATABASES

DB2, MySql, Oracle, Sybase, Microsoft SQL Server, Microsoft Access, Mongo DB, OpenWorks, IBM WebSphere MDM

SOURCE CONTROL SYSTEMS

Git, TFVC, ClearCase, SVN, CVS, VSS

FRAMEWORKS

Java (AWT, Swing, J2EE, Servlets, JSP, EJB), .NET, Spring, Hibernate, JUnit, log4j, C4.

PLATFORMS

OSDU, Eclipse RCP, Appian, JourneyApps, DecisionSpace, CUDA

TOOLKITS

OpenInventor (3D viewer), GeoToolkit.NET (2D viewer), Flexera (licensing), Ranorex (test automation), InstallShield (installer), AG Grid.

IDES

Eclipse IDE, MS Visual Studio

CI/CD

QuickBuild, TFS Build, Ant, Maven

PRODUCTIVITY / PROJECT MANAGEMENT

ChatGPT, Sunsama, TFS, Bugzilla, MS Office, MS Project, PeopleSoft, Rally, SharePoint

OTHER

Structurizr, Oracle IFS content management system, SAP, Fieldglass, Microsoft Teams, GoToMeeting, Zoom